# Linjian Ma

+1 217 979 7114 \$\displays \text{lma16@illinois.edu} \$\displays \text{linjianma.github.io}\$ github/Linkedin: linjianma

#### RESEARCH STATEMENT

My research interests lie in the intersection of numerical algorithms, high performance computing, quantum simulation and machine learning. In particular, I'm now focusing on developing efficient algorithms for tensor networks with applications in data analytics and quantum simulation. In addition, I'm also working on optimization and efficient compression methods of neural networks.

## EDUCATION BACKGROUNDS

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

August 2019 - Expected 2024

PhD, Computer Science, Advisor: Edgar Solomonik

Area: Scientific Computing

University of California, Berkeley

August 2018 - May 2019

MEng, Computer Science, Advisor: Michael Mahoney Major GPA: 3.94/4.0

Track: Data Science & Systems

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign August 2016 - May 2018

MS, Mechanical Engineering, Advisor: N.R. Aluru GPA: 3.97/4.0

Concentration: Computational Science and Engineering

Zhejiang University August 2012 - June 2016

BE, Energy Engineering, Advisor: Tao Wang and Zhongyang Luo GPA: 3.95/4.0 Ranking: 1/155

Graduate with Honors, Chu Kochen Honors College

# **EXPERIENCES**

## Lab for Parallel Numerical Algorithms, UIUC

August 2019 - Now

Research Assistant, Advisor: Edgar Solomonik

Topic: Tensor decomposition, automatic tensor differentiation and their applications

## Wave Computing & Berkeley AI Research (BAIR)

May 2019 - August 2019

Machine Learning Intern, Advisor: Sylvain Flamant

Topic: Compressing large scale neural networks based on second order information

#### RiseLab, UC Berkeley August 2018 - May 2019

Research Assistant, Advisor: Michael Mahoney

Capstone project: Second order optimization of neural network learning

## Lab for Parallel Numerical Algorithms, UIUC

May 2018 - July 2018

Research Intern, Advisor: Edgar Solomonik

Topic: Pairwise perturbation and multigrid in alternating least squares for tensor decomposition

## Beckman Institute, UIUC

August 2016 - December 2017

Research Assistant, Advisor: N.R. Aluru

Thesis: A multiscale model for the oxide ion conducting and proton conducting solid oxide cells

## **PUBLICATIONS**

[1] Sheng Shen, Zhen Dong, Jiayu Ye, Linjian Ma, Zhewei Yao, Amir Gholami, Michael W. Mahoney, Kurt Keutzer, Q-BERT: Hessian Based Ultra Low Precision Quantization of BERT, arXiv:1909.05840 [cs.CL], September, 2019. [link]

- [2] Linjian Ma\*, Gabe Montague\*, Jiayu Ye\*, Zhewei Yao, Amir Gholami, Kurt Keutzer, Michael W. Mahoney, Inefficiency of K-FAC for Large Batch Size Training, arXiv:1903.06237 [cs.LG], March, 2019. [link]
- [3] Linjian Ma and Edgar Solomonik, Accelerating Alternating Least Squares for Tensor Decomposition by Pairwise Perturbation, arXiv:1811.10573 [math.NA], November, 2018. [link]
- [4] Linjian Ma, Pikee Priya, and N. R. Aluru, A Multiscale Model for Electrochemical Reactions in LSCF Based Solid Oxide Cells, Journal of the Electrochemical Society, 2018, 165: F1232-F1241. [link]

## PRESENTATIONS

- [1] Linjian Ma and Edgar Solomonik, Accelerating Alternating Least Squares for Tensor Decomposition by Pairwise Perturbation, Scientific Computing Seminar, 6th March, 2019, Berkeley, CA.
- [2] Linjian Ma and N.R. Aluru, A Multiscale Model for the Reactive Mechanisms in Proton/Oxide Ion Conducting Solid Oxide Cells, PIRE Monthly Meething, 31st August, 2017, Champaign, IL.
- [3] Linjian Ma and N.R. Aluru, A Multiscale Model for the Oxygen Reduction and Oxidation Reactions in LSCF Based Solid Oxide Cells, 14th US National Congress on Computational Mechanics, 19th July, 2017, Montreal, Canada.

## HONORS AND AWARDS

Computer Science Gene Golub Fellowship, UIUC	2019
Graduate with Honor, ZJU	2016
Meritorious Winner, Mathematical Contest In Modeling (MCM)	2015
National Scholarship for Undergraduate, ZJU	2014
The First Class Scholarship for Outstanding Students, ZJU	2013 - 2014
The First Prize in China Undergraduates Mathematical Contest	2013

#### **SKILLS**

Programming Language ML Frameworks	es C/C++, Python, SQL, Bash, MATLAB, CUDA Pytorch, Tensorflow	
SELECTED COURSEWORK		
UIUC	Applied Physics: Intermediate Heat Transfer, Thermal & Statistical Physics,	
	Molecular Electronic Structure, Mathematical Methods II	
	Computational Science: Finite Element Analysis, Computational Mechanics,	
	Numerical Fluid Dynamics, Atomic Scale Simulations, Numerical Analysis	
	Computer Science: Parallel Programming, Computer System Organization,	
	Algorithm, Distributed Systems, Parallel Numerical Algorithms	
UC Berkeley	ML: Introduction to Machine Learning, Convex Optimization,	
	Understanding Deep Neural Networks, Principles of Data Science	
Zhejiang University	Applied Math: Mathematical Analysis(honor),	
	Ordinary/Partial Differential Equations, Probability and Statistics	
	Applied Physics: Physics(honor), General Chemistry, Fluid Dynamics,	
	Mechanics, Thermodynamics, Heat Transfer, Electromagnetic Fields & Waves	
	Computer Science: Discrete Mathematics, C Programming Language,	

Computational Methods